Delve into the darkness.
Thor: The Dark World is a action, adventure,
fantasy film directed by Alan Taylor.
Thor fights to restore order across the cosmos… but an ancient race led by the
vengeful Malekith returns to plunge the universe back into darkness.
Faced with an enemy that even Odin and Asgard cannot withstand, Thor must embark on his most perilous and personal
journey yet, one that will reunite him with Jane Foster and force him to sacrifice everything to save us all.
Thor, played by Chris Hemsworth.
Jane Foster, played by Natalie Portman.
Loki, played by Tom Hiddleston.
Malekith, played by Christopher Eccleston.
Odin, played by Anthony Hopkins.
Sif, played by Jaimie Alexander.
Thor: The Dark World is a 2013 American superhero film based on the Marvel Comics character Thor,
produced by Marvel Studios and distributed by Walt Disney Studios Motion Pictures.
It is the sequel to Thor (2011) and the eighth film in
the Marvel Cinematic Universe (MCU).
The film was directed by Alan Taylor from a screenplay by Christopher Yost and
the writing team of Christopher Markus and Stephen McFeely.
It stars Chris Hemsworth as Thor alongside Natalie Portman, Tom Hiddleston, Stellan Skarsgård, Idris Elba, Christopher Eccleston, Adewale
Akinnuoye-Agbaje, Kat Dennings, Ray Stevenson, Zachary Levi, Tadanobu Asano, Jaimie Alexander, Rene Russo, and Anthony Hopkins.
In the film, Thor and Loki (Hiddleston) team up to save
the Nine Realms from the Dark Elves.
Development of a sequel to Thor began in April 2011 when producer Kevin Feige
announced plans for it to follow the MCU crossover film The Avengers (2012).
In July, Thor director Kenneth Branagh withdrew from the sequel.
Taylor was hired to replace him as director in January 2012.
The supporting cast filled out that August with the hiring of
Eccleston and Akinnuoye-Agbaje as the film's villains.
Filming took place from September to December 2012, primarily in
Surrey, England, as well as in Iceland and London.
Taylor wanted the film to be more grounded than Thor, inspired
by his work on Game of Thrones (2011–2019).
He hired Carter Burwell to compose the score, but
Marvel replaced Burwell with Brian Tyler.
Thor: The Dark World premiered at the Odeon Leicester Square in London on October 22, 2013, and
was released in the United States on November 8, as part of Phase Two of the MCU.
The film was a commercial success, grossing over $644 million worldwide
and becoming the tenth highest-grossing film of 2013.
It received praise for the performances of Hemsworth and Hiddleston, visual effects, and
action sequences, but was criticized for its generic villain and lack of depth.
Retrospectively, Taylor expressed dissatisfaction with the film and said Marvel
substantially altered it from his original vision during post-production.
Two sequels have been released: Thor: Ragnarok (2017)
and Thor: Love and Thunder (2022).
The film explores themes of superhero, based on comic, hostile
takeover, norse mythology, aftercreditsstinger.
The tone is dark.